Guide to the Freshman Outdoor Orientation Trips, Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Freshman Outdoor Orientation Trips, records
1982-2017
RU 1148
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2.63
(4 boxes)
The records consist of participant rosters, trip evaluations, and administrative files from the Freshman Outdoor Orientation Trips (FOOT).
General
Forms part of Yale Record Group 40 (YRG 40), Records of Yale clubs, societies, and organizations.
Conditions Governing Access
The records are restricted until January 1, 2092.
Scope and Contents
The records consist of participant rosters, trip evaluations, and administrative files from the Freshman Outdoor Orientation Trips (FOOT).
Biographical / Historical
FOOT was started in 1984 by two undergrads, Jamie Williams and Greg Felt. They had both just completed a NOLS course and were excited about the prospect of introducing a similar experience as an orientation for incoming first-years. With a group of like-minded students —the first CORE— they started talking to administrators about the possibility of starting such a program. The administration was skeptical at first, and told them to seek out someone they could hire as a coordinator. This would lead them to Cilla Kellert, a NOLS graduate, former Outward Bound instructor and Yale Forestry School graduate, who has been with the program since it started.
At the beginning, FOOT was very small: just 12 leaders on 6 trips to the Catskills. The model they came up with, however, would come to define the FOOT experience — 4-6 day backpacking trips led by two co-leaders, who help to bring a sense of community and fun to the whole endeavor. When students return to Yale, they are pumped to begin college- having had a tremendous experience in the great outdoors and having formed friendships that will last for the next four years and beyond.
Related Materials
Undergraduate Affairs, Yale University, records of the dean (RU 95); accessions 1990-A-157 and 1990-A-016.
College students; Yale University -- Students
- Records, Accession 2017-A-071
  - Annual newsletters
    - 1992-2003 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 2004-2011 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 2012-2017 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Leader manuals
    - 1996-2005 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 2006-2017 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Brochures, 1988-2017 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - T-shirt designs, 1985-2003 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Promotional ephemera, Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Proposal to establish the Freshman Outdoor Orientation Trips (FOOT), 1985 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Early proposals and chronology, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - By-laws and report, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Faculty Advisory Committee (FAC), 1985-1996 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Leadership training, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Schedules, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - News clippings, 1985-2010 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Leader introductions, 2016 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Alumni trips, 1995-2004 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Surveys and report, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Menus and food ephemera, 1985-2015 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, 1999-2002 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - FOOT lore, 2000-2008 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Official programs, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Summer mailings-masters, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - FOOT leadership selection, 1985-2002 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Deceased leaders, 1993-2012 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Trips for Outdoor Enjoyment (TOE), 1988 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Harvest trips, 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Harvard Freshman Outdoor Program (FOP), 1982-1984 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Medical School Outdoor Orientation Trip (MOOT), 1998 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - FOOT co-coordinators (CORE), 2014-2016 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - FOOT leader daily journals, 1985-1999 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Participant rosters
    - 1985 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - 1986 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - 1987 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - 1988 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - 1989 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - 1990 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - 1991 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - 1992 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - 1993 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - 1994 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - 1995 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - 1996 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - 1997 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - 1998 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - 1999 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - 2000 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - 2001 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - 2002 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - 2003 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - 2004 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - 2005 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - 2006 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - 2007 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - 2008 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - 2009 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - 2010 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - 2011 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - 2012 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - 2013 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - 2014 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - 2015 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - 2016 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Evaluations, 1985-1988 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Evaluation masters, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Leader training evaluations, Undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Trip evaluations, Undated (Box 2, Folder 36-41)
  - Trip evaluations, Undated (Box 3, Folder 1-7)
  - "Yale Orientation", Undated (Box 4)